[
  {
    "question": "How are the boundaries of Arctic natural zones determined?",
    "answer": "Climatic conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are thermal springs formed in tectonically active zones?",
    "answer": "Underground heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are underground caves formed?",
    "answer": "Dissolution"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can changes in trade policy affect the availability of food products?",
    "answer": "Regulation of imports"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can ocean currents influence climatic conditions?",
    "answer": "Regulate temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can temporal changes be integrated into cartographic analyses?",
    "answer": "Data tracking"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did climate changes in the late Pleistocene affect the migration of Homo sapiens?",
    "answer": "New routes"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did demographic changes in Europe in the 20th century affect migration?",
    "answer": "Population increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did demographic growth in India in the 20th century affect migration?",
    "answer": "Urbanization"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did past climate change affect the distribution of biomes?",
    "answer": "Shift of zones"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did the migration of peoples affect the social structure of the Ottoman Empire?",
    "answer": "Ethnic diversity"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do demographic changes affect the spatial structure of megacities?",
    "answer": "Alter the structure"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do international trade barriers affect food availability?",
    "answer": "Increase in prices"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do ocean currents affect natural zones?",
    "answer": "Change the climate"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do paleogeographic studies influence the understanding of modern ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Through historical data"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do polar regions affect global atmospheric circulation?",
    "answer": "Formation of cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do regions adapt to changes in the global economy?",
    "answer": "Investing in technology"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do socio-economic zones affect globalization?",
    "answer": "Stimulate trade"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do zones support international trade?",
    "answer": "Reduction of tariffs"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does a change in the heat balance affect global climate change?",
    "answer": "Changes the temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does biological activity accelerate mineralization processes in soils?",
    "answer": "biogenic processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does climate change affect landscape dynamics in polar regions?",
    "answer": "Ice melting"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does climate change affect the processes of humus formation?",
    "answer": "Decrease or increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does digitalization affect the management of urban systems?",
    "answer": "Optimization"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does global warming affect ocean currents?",
    "answer": "Slows down"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does global warming affect population distribution?",
    "answer": "Climate-induced migration"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does globalization affect the international legal system?",
    "answer": "It unifies it"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does paleogeography determine changes in the levels of ancient seas?",
    "answer": "By layers"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does sea level rise affect coastal ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Coastal erosion"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does seismic activity affect river valleys?",
    "answer": "Change in flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the chemical composition of the oceans change during active volcanic activity?",
    "answer": "Increase in acidity"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the climate change after major eruptions?",
    "answer": "Cooling"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the interaction of organic and mineral components affect the agronomic value of soil?",
    "answer": "Improves fertility"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the presence of permafrost affect flora?",
    "answer": "Limits growth"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does urbanization affect the unemployment rate?"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the age of rocks determined by radiometric dating?",
    "answer": "Isotopic analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the speed of tectonic processes determined in different regions?",
    "answer": "Satellite data"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the structure of global finance changing under the influence of globalization?",
    "answer": "Diversification of assets"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which Eastern European country is the currency named after a national symbol or cultural element?",
    "answer": "Ukraine"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which Eastern European country is the currency named after a national symbol?",
    "answer": "Moldovan leu"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which South American country is the currency's name related to silver, even though the country is not known for mining this metal?",
    "answer": "Argentina"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which country does the name of the currency originate from a word meaning trade route in ancient times?",
    "answer": "Iran"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which country has the average life expectancy increased by 10 years since 1990?",
    "answer": "China"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which country is the currency named after an ancient era associated with a great conqueror?",
    "answer": "Iranian rial"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which landlocked Central American country is the currency named after a major Spanish island?",
    "answer": "Paraguay"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which natural zone do swampy landscapes prevail?",
    "answer": "Swamp"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of Asia is the rural population decreasing the most?",
    "answer": "East Asia"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which region is the UTC+8:45 time zone used?",
    "answer": "Southern Australia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the capital located on the island of Borneo, known for its tropical forests.",
    "answer": "Bandar Seri Begawan"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which peninsula in Asia are ancient Buddhist monuments located?",
    "answer": "Indochina"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which river is Angel Falls located?",
    "answer": "Churun"
  },
  {
    "question": "The currency of which country is called 'cedi', and it is known for its history of gold-rich lands?",
    "answer": "Ghana"
  },
  {
    "question": "The phenomenon of 'singing dunes' occurs in?",
    "answer": "Taklamakan"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the causes of sulfate crust formation in arid soils?",
    "answer": "Evaporation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the consequences of weathering in arid zones?",
    "answer": "Erosion of rocks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the environmental consequences associated with anthropogenic activities in arid regions?"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the forces called that govern the movement of lithospheric plates?"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the long-term geological consequences of volcanic eruptions?",
    "answer": "Formation of new landscapes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main differences between Arctic landscapes and other zones?",
    "answer": "Precipitation transfer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the prospects for local languages in the context of globalization?",
    "answer": "Decline"
  },
  {
    "question": "What atmospheric phenomenon alters the stability of the tropical climate?",
    "answer": "Atmospheric waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "What atmospheric process causes hurricane winds and heavy rains in the tropics?",
    "answer": "Cyclone"
  },
  {
    "question": "What atmospheric processes lead to the formation of the aurora?",
    "answer": "interaction of particles"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cataclysm is caused by underwater earthquakes?",
    "answer": "Tsunami"
  },
  {
    "question": "What catastrophic process can lead to the complete destruction of ecosystems over large areas in a short time?",
    "answer": "Volcanic eruption"
  },
  {
    "question": "What challenges do global cities face in the context of globalization?",
    "answer": "Increasing urbanization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes are caused by sharp temperature fluctuations in the troposphere?",
    "answer": "Instability"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes in ocean currents contribute to the formation of extreme weather conditions?",
    "answer": "El Niño"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes in plate tectonics are studied in paleogeography?",
    "answer": "Continental drift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes occur in soils with prolonged use for agricultural purposes?",
    "answer": "Depletion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What changes occur in the atmosphere due to ice melting?",
    "answer": "Change in albedo"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes active continental margins?",
    "answer": "Seismic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What climate changes affect deserts?",
    "answer": "Global warming"
  },
  {
    "question": "What climate changes are associated with changes in ocean currents?"
  },
  {
    "question": "What climate changes were caused by continental drift?",
    "answer": "Change in precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What concept describes the merging of urban agglomerations into a single megalopolitan area?",
    "answer": "Megalopolis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What conditions contribute to the formation of geothermal springs?",
    "answer": "Tectonic faults"
  },
  {
    "question": "What contributes to the acceleration of transnational capital flows?",
    "answer": "Financial technologies"
  },
  {
    "question": "What data was used to study ancient continental drift?",
    "answer": "Fossils"
  },
  {
    "question": "What distinguishes an agro-climatic zone from an agro-ecological zone?",
    "answer": "Temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ecological adaptations are characteristic of desert plants?",
    "answer": "Thick stems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ecological functions do forests perform in ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Absorption of carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ecosystems are formed in conditions where the ground temperature is constantly below zero?",
    "answer": "Tundra"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does the alpine climate have on soil formation processes?",
    "answer": "Slowing down"
  },
  {
    "question": "What effect does the colloidal fraction have on soil structure?",
    "answer": "Stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "What explains the movement of lithospheric plates over the asthenosphere?",
    "answer": "Convection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor influences the formation of river terraces?",
    "answer": "Soil erosion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor limits the spread of tropical species to temperate latitudes?",
    "answer": "Temperature gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor significantly increases the likelihood of a mudflow in mountainous areas?",
    "answer": "Heavy rains"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors contribute to the international competitiveness of zones?",
    "answer": "Innovation and technology"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors contributed to migrations during the Renaissance?",
    "answer": "Religious upheavals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors determine the choice of location for a zone?",
    "answer": "Infrastructure"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors determine the occurrence of polar auroras?",
    "answer": "Solar activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors determine the richness of fauna in deserts?",
    "answer": "Availability of water"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence changes in Arctic species populations?",
    "answer": "Climate change"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the development of thermokarst formations?",
    "answer": "Soil temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of a desert biome?",
    "answer": "Low precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of forest-steppe ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Moisture balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of paleovolcanoes?",
    "answer": "Tectonic movements"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of rare earth elements?",
    "answer": "Geological activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of rare earth metal deposits?",
    "answer": "Hydrothermal processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the formation of tornadoes?",
    "answer": "Different temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors influence the rate of coastal cliff erosion?",
    "answer": "Wave energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factors primarily influence the distribution of biomes on continents?",
    "answer": "Climatic conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What faunal adaptations allow animals to survive in desert conditions?",
    "answer": "Hyperthermal resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What feature of the volcanoes on Io makes them unique in the Solar System?",
    "answer": "Superactive volcanoes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What features accompany divergent boundaries?",
    "answer": "Rifting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What forces cause continental drift?",
    "answer": "Convection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What fossil data helps determine the ancient latitude of continents?",
    "answer": "Paleomagnetic directions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What geochemical phenomenon affects the evolution of soils in carbonate zones?",
    "answer": "Decarbonization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What geological factors influence the formation of volcanoes in a region?",
    "answer": "Plate tectonics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What geological phenomenon causes continental drift?",
    "answer": "Tectonic processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What geological processes determine the formation of mud volcanoes on continental margins?",
    "answer": "Diapirism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What geomorphological features are characteristic of the tropics?",
    "answer": "Mangrove swamps"
  },
  {
    "question": "What global initiatives support food security?",
    "answer": "UN programs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact do migration processes have on the genetic diversity of species?",
    "answer": "Gene flow"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact do multinational corporations (MNCs) have on the economic development of countries?",
    "answer": "Accelerate development"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact do polar ecosystems have on global ocean currents?",
    "answer": "Climate regulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact do volcanic eruptions have on the formation of mountain ranges?",
    "answer": "Tectonic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact does the movement of tectonic plates have on the parameters of ocean currents?",
    "answer": "Change in strength"
  },
  {
    "question": "What impact does volcanic activity have on biodiversity?",
    "answer": "Creation of new niches"
  },
  {
    "question": "What influence does relief have on the distribution of precipitation in climate zones?",
    "answer": "Barrier"
  },
  {
    "question": "What infrastructure changes contribute to increasing population density in cities?",
    "answer": "Transportation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What initiates the formation of geysers in volcanic areas?",
    "answer": "Geothermal heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is formed when an oceanic plate interacts with a continental plate?",
    "answer": "Mountain ranges"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is isostasy in the context of geology?",
    "answer": "Equilibrium of the crust"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of Easter Island?",
    "answer": "Hanga Roa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of Eritrea?",
    "answer": "Asmara"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of Malawi?",
    "answer": "Lilongwe"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of Suriname?",
    "answer": "Paramaribo"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of Zimbabwe?",
    "answer": "Harare"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the capital of the country Micronesia?",
    "answer": "Palikir"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the currency of the country located at the crossroads of Europe and Asia, known for its ancient crosses?",
    "answer": "Lari"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the key challenge facing zones?",
    "answer": "Competition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the largest active volcano in the world?",
    "answer": "Mauna Loa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the length of the Mississippi River?",
    "answer": "3730 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the longest river in Asia?",
    "answer": "Yangtze"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main factor in the formation of fractured slopes?",
    "answer": "Freezing of water"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most common ecosystem on Arctic islands?",
    "answer": "Tundra"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most pressing issue for agriculture in the monsoon zone?",
    "answer": "Floods"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the peninsula that was a key location in medieval trade between the East and the West?",
    "answer": "Arabian"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the river that flows through the most populous city in China?",
    "answer": "Yangtze"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the river that forms the border between Mali and Senegal?",
    "answer": "Senegal"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the zone where lithospheric plates diverge?",
    "answer": "Rift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the powerful release of gas and ash from cracks in the ground called?",
    "answer": "Fumarole"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process called where ocean currents interact with underwater ridges, causing vertical mixing and changes in ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Upwelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the rarest form of volcanic cone?",
    "answer": "Folded"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of capillary forces in soil hydrology?",
    "answer": "Moisture transport"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of soil microflora in the transformation of organic matter into humus?",
    "answer": "significant"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the significance of ancient ocean currents for understanding paleogeographic changes?",
    "answer": "Continental movement"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the significance of ocean currents for agriculture?",
    "answer": "Regulate climate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the significance of the mineralogical composition of rocks for their resistance to weathering?",
    "answer": "The significance is critical"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the structure called that represents a fracture in the ocean floor where two tectonic plates converge?",
    "answer": "Mid-ocean ridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the zone between the tundra and the ice deserts called?",
    "answer": "Subarctic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is volcanic glass called?",
    "answer": "Obsidian"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mechanisms alter the structure of clouds at the equator?",
    "answer": "Convection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mechanisms influence the formation of endemic species?",
    "answer": "Genetic isolation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mechanisms lead to the formation of geographical barriers?",
    "answer": "Tectonic movements"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used for oil field evaluation?",
    "answer": "Seismic survey"
  },
  {
    "question": "What method is used to study the dynamics of tectonic plates?",
    "answer": "Satellite geodesy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What methods are used to determine the optimal map scale for a specific task?",
    "answer": "Task analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What methods are used to predict volcanic eruptions?",
    "answer": "Seismic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What methods are used to study ancient ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Fossil analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What modern method is used to study changes in glaciers in polar regions?",
    "answer": "Laser scanning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What morphological changes occur in Arctic glaciers?",
    "answer": "Ice recrystallization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural conditions are necessary for the formation of an artesian basin?",
    "answer": "Confined aquifer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural conditions contribute to the formation of hyper-arid deserts?",
    "answer": "High insolation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural disaster can cause global changes in precipitation?",
    "answer": "El Niño"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural disaster can destroy entire ecosystems in a matter of minutes?",
    "answer": "Tsunami"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural disaster can occur due to a massive release of ash and gases into the atmosphere?",
    "answer": "Volcanic eruption"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural disaster can result from a sharp change in temperature gradients between land and ocean, causing powerful winds and heavy rainfall?",
    "answer": "Tropical cyclone"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural phenomenon can cause mass migration of people and animals over significant distances?",
    "answer": "Volcanic eruption"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural phenomenon can cause rapid changes in the chemical composition of the atmosphere?",
    "answer": "Volcanic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural process can cause a significant change in the water level of a reservoir as a result of dam activity?",
    "answer": "Dam burst"
  },
  {
    "question": "What natural process leads to the formation of new ice in polar regions?",
    "answer": "freezing of the ocean"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomena can intensify floods?",
    "answer": "Heavy rains and melting"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon allows international organizations to regulate global processes?",
    "answer": "Global governance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon can cause sea level changes due to tectonic activity?",
    "answer": "Isostatic equilibrium"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon can exacerbate flooding in coastal areas?",
    "answer": "Storm surges"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon can lead to mass death of marine life due to temperature changes?",
    "answer": "Thermal stress"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon contributes to the accelerated integration of markets?",
    "answer": "Globalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon contributes to the movement of lithospheric plates?",
    "answer": "Mantle"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon describes the movement of water in karst systems?",
    "answer": "Underground rivers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon determines the vertical separation of water masses in lakes?",
    "answer": "Stratification"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon explains the similarity of flora in South America and Africa?",
    "answer": "Continental drift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon is characteristic of the tectonic plate boundaries in the Pacific Ocean?",
    "answer": "Ring of Fire"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon leads to changes in the range boundaries of species in equatorial regions?",
    "answer": "Climatic fluctuations"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon often accompanies the process of subduction?",
    "answer": "Volcanism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What physico-chemical process contributes to the accumulation of clay in the lower soil horizons?",
    "answer": "Illuviation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What plant adaptations allow them to survive in extreme drought conditions?",
    "answer": "Succulents"
  },
  {
    "question": "What plays a key role in shaping the polar landscape?",
    "answer": "Glaciers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What political changes are associated with globalization?",
    "answer": "Integration is strengthened"
  },
  {
    "question": "What population movements occurred as a result of the economic crisis in 19th century Europe?",
    "answer": "To cities"
  },
  {
    "question": "What practices contribute to increasing biodiversity in agroecosystems?",
    "answer": "Crop rotation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process affects the rate of sedimentation in marine basins?",
    "answer": "Tectonic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process causes the formation of earthquakes at oceanic ridges?",
    "answer": "Divergence of plates"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process causes the formation of lakes in glacial valleys?",
    "answer": "Glacial erosion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process causes the reduction of ice cover in polar regions?",
    "answer": "Global warming"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process contributes to soil weathering in Arctic zones?",
    "answer": "Physical"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process controls the formation of thermocline layers in the seas?",
    "answer": "Temperature stratification"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process determines the formation of the hypergenesis zone on the Earth's surface?",
    "answer": "Weathering"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process determines the global circulation of oceanic waters?",
    "answer": "Thermohaline circulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process explains the uniqueness of Madagascar's species?",
    "answer": "Evolutionary isolation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process helps in the recovery of forests after natural disasters?",
    "answer": "restoration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is activated by excessive soil moisture?",
    "answer": "Gleying"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is responsible for the formation of funnel-shaped depressions in areas where carbonate rocks emerge?",
    "answer": "Karst activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process is responsible for the formation of submarine canyons?",
    "answer": "Turbidity currents"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to the formation of biodiversity in isolated water bodies?",
    "answer": "Evolutionary divergence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to the formation of geothermal fields?",
    "answer": "Volcanic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to the formation of large mountain ranges on continents?",
    "answer": "Continental collision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to the formation of oceanic plateaus?",
    "answer": "Plate tectonics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to the formation of volcanic geysers?",
    "answer": "Hydrothermal activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process leads to volcanic eruptions on island arcs?",
    "answer": "Subduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes affect global climate change at the ecosystem level?",
    "answer": "Biogeochemical cycles"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes affect terraces?",
    "answer": "Erosion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes are involved in the formation of polar vortices?",
    "answer": "Atmospheric circulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes cause fluctuations in ocean surface temperature?",
    "answer": "Thermal anomaly"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes characterize a transform boundary?",
    "answer": "Horizontal sliding"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes contribute to soil formation in different natural zones?",
    "answer": "Oxidation of organic matter"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes contribute to the formation of ancient marine deposits?",
    "answer": "Sedimentary processes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes contributed to the formation of the Great Plains in North America?",
    "answer": "Post-glacial sedimentation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes dominate the formation of rift valleys?",
    "answer": "tectonic movements"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes form the soil's ability to retain moisture?",
    "answer": "Capillarity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes lead to changes in river ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Pollution"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes lead to the formation of volcanic islands?",
    "answer": "Underwater volcanism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What processes regulate the global circulation of the atmosphere?",
    "answer": "Wind systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What property of magma determines its viscosity?",
    "answer": "Silicon content"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role did ocean currents play in ancient climates?",
    "answer": "Temperature regulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role did trade routes play in the migrations of peoples in the Mediterranean during antiquity?",
    "answer": "Economic benefits"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role do forests play in the global water cycle?",
    "answer": "Evaporation of moisture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role do hydrothermal solutions play in the formation of gold deposits?",
    "answer": "Transport of metals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role do natural zones play in the global cycle of substances?",
    "answer": "Carbon balance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role does erosion play in shaping the Earth's landscape?",
    "answer": "Formation of valleys"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role does hydrothermal activity play in geological processes?",
    "answer": "Ore formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role does hydrothermal activity play in the formation of ore deposits?",
    "answer": "Significant role"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role does mantle material play in volcanism?",
    "answer": "Source of magma"
  },
  {
    "question": "What social changes were caused by migration in Eastern Europe in the 21st century?",
    "answer": "Emigration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What soil property is determined by the presence of trivalent iron?",
    "answer": "Color"
  },
  {
    "question": "What strategies are used to address the problem of overpopulation in cities?",
    "answer": "Development of suburbs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What strategies are used to enhance the resilience of global food systems?",
    "answer": "Innovations in agrotechnology"
  },
  {
    "question": "What strategy do polar birds use to survive in harsh conditions?",
    "answer": "Migration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What structure connects the Scandinavian and Jutland peninsulas?",
    "answer": "Øresund Bridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "What substance determines the buffering capacity of soil?",
    "answer": "Humus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What survival mechanisms do animals in the desert use to conserve moisture?",
    "answer": "Minimizing losses"
  },
  {
    "question": "What survival strategies do animals use in the desert?",
    "answer": "Camouflage"
  },
  {
    "question": "What survival strategies do animals use to adapt to extreme temperature conditions in deserts?",
    "answer": "Nocturnal habits"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technologies help minimize environmental impact during gas extraction?",
    "answer": "Hydraulic fracturing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tectonic phenomenon can cause climate change?",
    "answer": "Plate shift"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tectonic processes influence the formation of underwater ridges in the Arctic?",
    "answer": "Seafloor spreading"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tool helps in mapping tectonic faults?",
    "answer": "Ground-penetrating radar"
  },
  {
    "question": "What trend is observed in the employment structure amid urbanization?",
    "answer": "Growth of services"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of geological faults are formed at convergent plate boundaries?",
    "answer": "Subduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of plate boundary is characterized by horizontal movement without rupture?",
    "answer": "Transform"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of plate movement leads to the formation of mountain ranges?",
    "answer": "Collision"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of plate movement leads to the formation of volcanic arcs?",
    "answer": "Subduction of plates"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of plate movement predominates in a fault zone?",
    "answer": "Transform"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of vegetation is common on Arctic coasts?",
    "answer": "Sphagnum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What unique form of life thrives in permafrost conditions?",
    "answer": "Cryophilic microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions lead to the formation of hurricanes?",
    "answer": "Warm oceans"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where in the world are the largest rubber processing enterprises concentrated?",
    "answer": "Malaysia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the largest biotechnology development center located?",
    "answer": "USA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the largest microchip manufacturing plant in the world located?",
    "answer": "Taiwan"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the world's largest palladium processing center located?",
    "answer": "Russia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Asian city is a leader in integrating public transportation with residential areas?",
    "answer": "Singapore"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Asian port is the largest for oil imports?",
    "answer": "Singapore"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which European city has the largest proportion of rural population?",
    "answer": "Bucharest"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which European country uses a currency whose name is associated with ancient sea conquerors?",
    "answer": "Sweden"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which European transport hub serves as a key link for freight transport through the Alps?",
    "answer": "Zurich"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which North American city is a leading center for telecommunications?",
    "answer": "New York"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which South American country has the highest migration growth?",
    "answer": "Chile"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which algorithm is used to minimize errors in coordinate transformation in cartography?",
    "answer": "Geodetic adjustment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which archipelago is located between the Barents Sea and the Kara Sea?",
    "answer": "Novaya Zemlya"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which archipelago is located north of Norway?",
    "answer": "Svalbard"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which areas can be most effective for sustainable development?",
    "answer": "Innovation hubs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which biogeographic zone has the lowest biomass per unit area despite its vastness?",
    "answer": "Arctic desert"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which biological processes are most affected by warming in the Arctic?",
    "answer": "Animal migration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which biomes are most affected by climate change?",
    "answer": "Arctic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which biotic processes influence the structure of ecosystems?",
    "answer": "Species competition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bridge is the longest in the world among railway bridges?",
    "answer": "Danyang-Kunshan"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cartography method corresponds to dividing the surface into squares?",
    "answer": "Square grid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cataclysm can cause power line breaks and building destruction due to strong winds?",
    "answer": "Hurricane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cataclysm is named after the Roman god of fire?",
    "answer": "Volcano"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which characteristic of a body of water determines its resilience to changes in water level?",
    "answer": "Capacity of the body of water"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city has the largest area of parks in the world?",
    "answer": "London"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in Asia is a key hub for oil and gas trade due to its strategic location?",
    "answer": "Dubai"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in Asia is considered a leader in medical research and innovation?",
    "answer": "Singapore"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in Asia is the main trading hub for gemstones?",
    "answer": "Hong Kong"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in North America is known for its innovations in sustainable architecture?",
    "answer": "Vancouver"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in Oceania stands out as a leading center for marine research and oceanography?"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in South America is known for having the largest emerald market?",
    "answer": "Bogotá"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in South America is recognized as a hub for financial technology and startups?",
    "answer": "São Paulo"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city in the USA switches to the UTC-5 time zone in the summer?",
    "answer": "Chicago"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city is known as the largest export hub for fruits in Spain?",
    "answer": "Valencia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city is the global center for international legal disputes?",
    "answer": "London"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city was known as Constantinople until 1930?",
    "answer": "Istanbul"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which climate elements can lead to drought?",
    "answer": "High temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country has the Tangier economic zone?",
    "answer": "Morocco"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country has the largest number of SEZs?",
    "answer": "China"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country in Africa is characterized by the highest proportion of urban population?",
    "answer": "Nigeria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country is known for creating the first successful Special Economic Zone (SEZ)?",
    "answer": "China"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country leads in silver production?",
    "answer": "Mexico"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country leads in the production of tin ore?",
    "answer": "China"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cultural phenomenon contributed to population migration in Europe during the Renaissance?",
    "answer": "humanism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which demographic indicator most strongly affects economic development?",
    "answer": "Population"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which economic factor most influences the global grain market?",
    "answer": "Subsidies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which element is most important for the prosperity of economic zones in North America?",
    "answer": "Technology"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which eruptions create lava plateaus?",
    "answer": "Basaltic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ethnic groups migrated to Oceania in ancient times?",
    "answer": "Austronesians"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which explorer was the first to reach South Georgia Island?",
    "answer": "James Cook"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factor has the greatest influence on the differences in climates of two closely located regions?",
    "answer": "Relief"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factor minimally affects soil acidity in the tropics?",
    "answer": "Minerals"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which geological process contributes to the formation of new volcanic islands?",
    "answer": "Plate subduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which geopolitical event can drastically change sea routes?",
    "answer": "Global warming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which historical document introduced the standard for time zones?",
    "answer": "The 1884 Convention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which international organization is responsible for the protection of the Arctic?",
    "answer": "Arctic Council"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which island uses UTC+12:45 during the summer?",
    "answer": "Chatham"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which island was central in the myths about Hercules?",
    "answer": "Erythrea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which lake in Scandinavia is known for underwater antiquities?",
    "answer": "Vättern"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which lake in South America is known for its reed boats?",
    "answer": "Titicaca"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which landforms indicate ancient tectonic processes?",
    "answer": "Rift valleys"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which landscape element is most susceptible to deflation?",
    "answer": "Sand"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which macro factor has the greatest impact on the regions of Eastern Europe?",
    "answer": "Economy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which mountain on the equator is illuminated by the sun all day?",
    "answer": "Kenya"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which natural zone includes areas with saline soils and minimal vegetation?",
    "answer": "Salt flats"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which natural zone includes shrub steppes?",
    "answer": "Patagonian Desert"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ocean is slowly expanding?",
    "answer": "Atlantic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the modern agricultural development directions is focused on increasing resilience to climate change?",
    "answer": "agroforestry"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which parameter controls the viscosity of mantle flows?",
    "answer": "Temperature regime"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which peak in the Himalayas has the largest vertical drop?",
    "answer": "Annapurna"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which peninsula played a key role in medieval trade between Europe and Asia?",
    "answer": "Asia Minor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process most radically changes the structure of an urban agglomeration?",
    "answer": "Migration flows"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process significantly influences the formation of soil profile texture and structure under strong wind conditions?",
    "answer": "Aeolian weathering"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process significantly influences the formation of thick humus horizons?",
    "answer": "humification"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which processes play a key role in climate change at the local level?",
    "answer": "Evaporation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which property of map projections helps to study climate changes?",
    "answer": "Preservation of shape"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which railway project in Africa promotes regional integration?",
    "answer": "Tanzanian Corridor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which railway route crosses the largest number of climate zones?",
    "answer": "Trans-Siberian Railway"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region has a half-hour offset from UTC-4?",
    "answer": "Venezuela"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region in Europe is known as a center for automotive research and development?",
    "answer": "Bavaria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region in India is the largest producer and exporter of spices, including cardamom and pepper?",
    "answer": "Kerala"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region in the world is known for the largest production of titanium ore?",
    "answer": "Australia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region most actively uses agrotechnologies to increase crop yields?",
    "answer": "North America"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region of the world is most vulnerable to changes in demographic structure due to migration?",
    "answer": "European Union"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river flows into Lake Chingozero?",
    "answer": "Soga"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river flows through the Amazon Basin?",
    "answer": "Amazon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river flows through the ancient city of Perge?",
    "answer": "Aksu"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river in Europe is known for its underground karst routes?",
    "answer": "Kraska"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river is considered the most famous in China?",
    "answer": "Yellow River"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which river is the longest on the Arabian Peninsula?",
    "answer": "Wadi Al-Rummah"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which sea covered Europe in the Mesozoic era?",
    "answer": "Tethys"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which seabird is best adapted to Arctic conditions?",
    "answer": "Guillemot"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which soil processes are determined by the hydrological regime of the area?",
    "answer": "Gleying"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which tectonic boundaries are characterized by plates moving in opposite directions?",
    "answer": "Transform boundaries"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which transport corridor passes through Finland?",
    "answer": "Northern"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which transport route connects China to London by rail?",
    "answer": "New Silk Road"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of plate interaction leads to the formation of deep-sea trenches?",
    "answer": "Subduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which volcanic eruption lasted the longest in human history?",
    "answer": "Kilauea, 1983-2018"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which volcano created the Hawaiian Islands?",
    "answer": "Mauna Loa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which world mountain is known for its unique horizontal layers?",
    "answer": "Mount Roraima"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who first used the triangulation method for cartography?",
    "answer": "Gerardus Mercator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first European to cross the Sahara Desert?",
    "answer": "Louis Jussieu"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first to cross Australia from south to north?",
    "answer": "John Eyre"
  }
]